{
  "2005": [
    {
      "question": "Supergene sulfide enrichment occurs:",
      "options": [
        "Below the water table",
        "Above the water table",
        "At depths independent of water table",
        "Both above and below the water table"
      ],
      "answer": "Below the water table"
    },
    {
      "question": "A mineral has steel-grey colour, metallic lustre, two sets of perfect octahedral cleavage and very high specific gravity. The mineral is:",
      "options": [
        "Galena",
        "Magnetite",
        "Molybdenite",
        "Barite"
      ],
      "answer": "Galena"
    },
    {
      "question": "Of the following, pick the mineral that is not associated with pegmatites:",
      "options": [
        "Mica",
        "Emerald",
        "Feldspar",
        "Kyanite"
      ],
      "answer": "Kyanite"
    }
  ],
  "2006": [
    {
      "question": "Chromite deposits result from:",
      "options": [
        "Early magmatic dissemination",
        "Early magmatic segregation",
        "Early magmatic injection",
        "Late magmatic residual fluid injection"
      ],
      "answer": "Early magmatic segregation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The largest known kyanite deposit in the world is in:",
      "options": [
        "Jharkhand",
        "Bihar",
        "Assam",
        "Tamil Nadu"
      ],
      "answer": "Jharkhand"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the following: Group I: P. Oil Q. Coal R. Lead - zinc S. Phosphate Group II: 1. Bokaro 2. Zawar 3. Jamar Kotra 4. Ankleshwar",
      "options": [
        "P-1, Q-3, R-2, S-4",
        "P-2, Q-4, R-3, S-1",
        "P-4, Q-1, R-3, S-2",
        "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3"
      ],
      "answer": "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3"
    }
  ],
  "2007": [
    {
      "question": "Which of the following processes of ore formation produces gold deposits in the form of reef?",
      "options": [
        "Hydrothermal",
        "Magmatic injection",
        "Magmatic segregation",
        "Supergene enrichment"
      ],
      "answer": "Hydrothermal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Beach placers in India are an important source of:",
      "options": [
        "Copper",
        "Lead",
        "Thorium",
        "Uranium"
      ],
      "answer": "Thorium"
    },
    {
      "question": "The reservoir rock for petroleum in Bombay High is:",
      "options": [
        "Feldspathic sandstone",
        "Graywacke",
        "Limestone",
        "Orthoquartzite"
      ],
      "answer": "Limestone"
    }
  ],
  "2008": [
    {
      "question": "A greyish brown coloured mineral of metallic lustre gives cherry red streak. The mineral is:",
      "options": [
        "Wolframite",
        "Hematite",
        "Chromite",
        "Magnetite"
      ],
      "answer": "Hematite"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hydrothermal deposits formed at a temperature range of 50° - 200° C are known as:",
      "options": [
        "Mesothermal",
        "Hypothermal",
        "Epithermal",
        "Telethermal"
      ],
      "answer": "Epithermal"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ascending ore-forming fluids within the earth's crust give rise to:",
      "options": [
        "Hypogene deposit",
        "Supergene deposit",
        "Syngenetic deposit",
        "Stratiform deposit"
      ],
      "answer": "Hypogene deposit"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the coalfields listed in Group I with their occurrences in States listed in Group II. Group I: P. Talchir Q. Nayveli R. Singrauli S. Jhingurda Group II: 1. Uttar Pradesh 2. Orrissa 3. Tamil Nadu 4. Madhya Pradesh",
      "options": [
        "P-1, Q-2, R-3, S-4",
        "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-1",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-1, S-2",
        "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3"
      ],
      "answer": "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the mineral deposits listed in Group I with their occurrences listed in Group II. Group I: P. Gold Q. Bauxite R. Lead-Zinc S. Diamond Group II: 1. Majhgawan 2. Zawarmala 3. Palamau 4. Hutti",
      "options": [
        "P-2, Q-1, R-3, S-4",
        "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1",
        "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3",
        "P-1, Q-3, R-4, S-2"
      ],
      "answer": "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1"
    }
  ],
  "2009": [
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is an ore mineral of uranium?",
      "options": [
        "Sphalerite",
        "Pitchblende",
        "Cassiterite",
        "Wolframite"
      ],
      "answer": "Pitchblende"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following minerals is characterized by black streak?",
      "options": [
        "Hematite",
        "Sphalerite",
        "Magnetite",
        "Malachite"
      ],
      "answer": "Magnetite"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tin and Tungsten mineralization is commonly associated with:",
      "options": [
        "Basalt",
        "Gabbro",
        "Dunite",
        "Granite"
      ],
      "answer": "Granite"
    }
  ],
  "2010": [
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is an INCORRECT statement?",
      "options": [
        "Siderite is an iron ore of carbonate composition",
        "Hematite is an iron ore with ferro-magnetic character",
        "Limonite is a hydrated iron ore",
        "Magnetite is an iron ore that crystallizes in an isometric system"
      ],
      "answer": "Hematite is an iron ore with ferro-magnetic character"
    },
    {
      "question": "Commercial magnesite deposit can be hosted in:",
      "options": [
        "Serpentinite",
        "Potassic Granite",
        "Gabbro",
        "Nepheline syenite"
      ],
      "answer": "Serpentinite"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the economic deposits in Group I with their corresponding occurrences in Group II. Group I: P. Lignite Q. Petroleum R. Copper S. Uranium Group II: 1. Jaduguda 2. Malanjkhand 3. Neyveli 4. Rudrasagar",
      "options": [
        "P-3, Q-4, R-1, S-2",
        "P-2, Q-4, R-1, S-3",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
        "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1"
      ],
      "answer": "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1"
    },
    {
      "question": "A copper-nickel-sulphide ore deposit occurring in the basal part of a layered gabbro can originate by the following process:",
      "options": [
        "Early magmatic segregation",
        "Late magmatic residual liquid segregation",
        "Early magmatic injection",
        "Late magmatic immiscible liquid segregation"
      ],
      "answer": "Late magmatic immiscible liquid segregation"
    }
  ],
  "2011": [
    {
      "question": "Match the item in Group-I with appropriate item in Group-II. Group I: (P) Beach placers, (Q) Sulfide chimney, (R) Bauxite, (S) Phosphorite. Group II: (1) Submarine hydrothermal system, (2) Mechanical concentration, (3) Biogenic, (4) Residual Concentration",
      "options": [
        "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1",
        "P-4, Q-1, R-3, S-2",
        "P-2, Q-1, R-4, S-3",
        "P-4, Q-2, R-3, S-1"
      ],
      "answer": "P-2, Q-1, R-4, S-3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Choose the correct sequence of ore minerals arranged in the increasing order of hardness.",
      "options": [
        "Pyrite < Galena < Sphalerite < Magnetite",
        "Galena < Sphalerite < Magnetite < Pyrite",
        "Pyrite < Magnetite < Sphalerite < Galena",
        "Galena < Sphalerite < Pyrite < Magnetite"
      ],
      "answer": "Galena < Sphalerite < Magnetite < Pyrite"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the given mineral species of gold is rare to form in nature?",
      "options": [
        "Au-sulfide",
        "Au-telluride",
        "Native Au",
        "Au-Ag alloy"
      ],
      "answer": "Au-sulfide"
    }
  ],
  "2012": [
    {
      "question": "Match the economic deposits in Group I with their Indian occurrences in Group II. Group I: (P) Coal, (Q) Manganese, (R) Magnesite, (S) Mica. Group II: (1) Balaghat, (2) Koderma, (3) Talcher, (4) Salem",
      "options": [
        "P-4, Q-1, R-3, S-2",
        "P-2, Q-1, R-4, S-3",
        "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1",
        "P-3, Q-1, R-4, S-2"
      ],
      "answer": "P-3, Q-1, R-4, S-2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Extensive hydrothermal alteration is generally associated with:",
      "options": [
        "Stratiform chromite deposit",
        "Quartz-pebble conglomerate-hosted gold deposit",
        "Superior-type iron deposit",
        "Porphyry copper deposit"
      ],
      "answer": "Porphyry copper deposit"
    },
    {
      "question": "Geiger Muller counter is commonly used for the exploration of:",
      "options": [
        "Bauxite deposit",
        "Pb-Zn deposit",
        "Uranium deposit",
        "Iron ore"
      ],
      "answer": "Uranium deposit"
    }
  ],
  "2013": [
    {
      "question": "Malachite and Azurite are characteristic ore minerals of:",
      "options": [
        "Gossan zone",
        "Zone of oxidation",
        "Zone of supergene enrichment",
        "Protore"
      ],
      "answer": "Zone of oxidation"
    }
  ],
  "2014": [
    {
      "question": "Which of the following physical properties characterize galena?",
      "options": [
        "Prismatic form",
        "Cherry red streak",
        "Yellow colour",
        "High specific gravity"
      ],
      "answer": "High specific gravity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Among the following ores, of which is gossan a characteristic surface indicator?",
      "options": [
        "Pyrite-chalcopyrite",
        "Chromite-magnetite",
        "Pyrolusite-psilomelane",
        "Columbite-tantalite"
      ],
      "answer": "Pyrite-chalcopyrite"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the mineral deposits in Group-I with the localities of their occurrences in Group-II. Group-I: (P) Lignite, (Q) Fluorite, (R) Chromite, (S) Sphalerite-Galena. Group-II: (1) Dariba, (2) Noamundi, (3) Panandhro, (4) Amba Dongar, (5) Naushahi",
      "options": [
        "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-5",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-5, S-1",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
        "P-4, Q-5, R-1, S-2"
      ],
      "answer": "P-3, Q-4, R-5, S-1"
    },
    {
      "question": "'Comb structure' with 'symmetrical banding' is formed by:",
      "options": [
        "Early magmatic process",
        "Hydrothermal process",
        "Chemical sedimentary process",
        "Residual concentration process"
      ],
      "answer": "Hydrothermal process"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the items of Group-I with appropriate items in Group-II. Group-I: (P) Banded Iron Formation, (Q) Andesite porphyry, (R) Lamproite, (S) Pegmatite. Group-II: (1) Copper, (2) Diamond, (3) Rare metals, (4) Blue dust",
      "options": [
        "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3",
        "P-3, Q-2, R-4, S-1",
        "P-4, Q-3, R-1, S-2",
        "P-4, Q-1, R-3, S-2"
      ],
      "answer": "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3"
    }
  ],
  "2015": [
    {
      "question": "Identify the mineral which has specific gravity >5, hardness <3 and gives grey streak.",
      "options": [
        "Barite",
        "Sphalerite",
        "Graphite",
        "Galena"
      ],
      "answer": "Galena"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following mineral deposit is formed exclusively by surface geological processes?",
      "options": [
        "Wollastonite",
        "Asbestos",
        "Corundum",
        "Bauxite"
      ],
      "answer": "Bauxite"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the metals listed in Group-I with their ores in Group-II. Group-I (i) Tin (ii) Tungsten (iii) Copper (iv) Manganese Group -II (P) Scheelite (Q) Pyrolusite (R) Cassiterite (S) Borate",
      "options": [
        "(i) - R, (ii) - P, (iii) - S, (iv) - Q",
        "(i) - Q, (ii) - P, (iii) - S, (iv) - R",
        "(i) - R, (ii) - Q, (iii) - P, (iv) - S",
        "(i) - P, (ii) - S, (iii) - R, (iv) - Q"
      ],
      "answer": "(i) - R, (ii) - P, (iii) - S, (iv) - Q"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pyrite-chalcopyrite-bearing copper ore body has undergone supergene enrichment. Choose the correct statement(s). (Multiple Select Question)",
      "options": [
        "Limonite is present in the gossan zone",
        "Cuprite is present in the zone of oxidation",
        "Chalcocite is present in the zone of supergene enrichment",
        "Malachite is present in the primary zone"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Limonite is present in the gossan zone",
        "Cuprite is present in the zone of oxidation",
        "Chalcocite is present in the zone of supergene enrichment"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "From the given equation, calculate how many moles of magnetite will be produced by the reduction of 1 (one) mole of hematite (answer to be given up to 3 decimal places).\n\n6Fe₂O₃ → 4Fe₃O₄ + O₂",
      "options": [],
      "answer": "0.667"
    },
    {
      "question": "An ore body showing ‘saddle reef’ structure is formed by:",
      "options": [
        "Early magmatic crystallization process",
        "Liquid immiscibility",
        "Hydrothermal process",
        "Metamorphic process"
      ],
      "answer": "Hydrothermal process"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct? (Multiple Select Question)",
      "options": [
        "Rajpura-Dariba in Rajasthan is a working Pb-Zn deposit",
        "Iron ore is mined in Noamundi, Odisha",
        "The largest copper mine in India is located in Malanjkhand, Madhya Pradesh",
        "Manganese deposit is found in the Mansar Formation, Maharashtra"
      ],
      "answer": ["Rajpura-Dariba in Rajasthan is a working Pb-Zn deposit", "The largest copper mine in India is located in Malanjkhand, Madhya Pradesh", "Manganese deposit is found in the Mansar Formation, Maharashtra"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Petroleum producing basins of India belong to: (Multiple Select Question)",
      "options": [
        "Cambrian",
        "Cretaceous",
        "Tertiary",
        "Quaternary"
      ],
      "answer": ["Cretaceous", "Tertiary"]
    }
  ],
  "2016": [
    {
      "question": "The total metal content of a mineable 40m × 40m × 3m ore block having bulk density 2.75 g/cm³ and assay value 1.5 wt % Cu is _____ metric tonnes.",
      "options": [],
      "answer": "198"
    },
    {
      "question": "Coking coal in India is found in",
      "options": [
        "Neyvelli, Tamil Nadu",
        "Jharia, Jharkhand",
        "Palana, Rajasthan",
        "Garampani, Meghalya"
      ],
      "answer": "Jharia, Jharkhand"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the ore deposits in Group I with the localities in Group II. Group I: i) Copper, ii) Lead-Zinc, iii) Manganese, iv) Bauxite Group II: P) Balaghat, M.P., Q) Panchpatmali, Odisha, R) Rampura-Agucha, Rajasthan, S) Khetri, Rajasthan",
      "options": [
        "i-P, ii-S, iii-R, iv-Q",
        "i-S, ii-R, iii-P, iv-Q",
        "i-P, ii-R, iii-Q, iv-S",
        "i-S, ii-Q, iii-R, iv-P"
      ],
      "answer": "i-S, ii-R, iii-P, iv-Q"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following ore deposit(s) is/are formed only by hydrothermal process? (Multiple Select Question)",
      "options": [
        "‘Sn-W’ ore associated with greisenised rock",
        "Layered type chromite ore associated with dunite-peridotite-pyroxenite",
        "Vein type gold ore associated with greenstone belt",
        "Ni-Cu sulphide ore associated with gabbroic rocks"
      ],
      "answer": ["‘Sn-W’ ore associated with greisenised rock", "Vein type gold ore associated with greenstone belt"]
    }
  ],
  "2017": [
    {
      "question": "Identify the correct match between mineral/ore and its physical property.",
      "options": [
        "Hematite - Yellow streak",
        "Barite - High specific gravity",
        "Psilomelane - Comb structure",
        "Azurite - Distinctive green colour"
      ],
      "answer": "Barite - High specific gravity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the mineral deposits in Group I with their Indian occurrences in Group II. Group I: P. Chromite, Q. Magnesite, R. Mica, S. Phosphorite Group II: 1. Jhamarkotra, Rajasthan, 2. Gudur, Andhra Pradesh, 3. Byrapur, Karnataka, 4. Chalk Hills, Tamil Nadu",
      "options": [
        "P-1, Q-4, R-3, S-2",
        "P-3, Q-2, R-4, S-1",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
        "P-2, Q-1, R-3, S-4"
      ],
      "answer": "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1"
    },
    {
      "question": "A horizontal cylindrical ore body (diameter = 20 m, length = 200 m) has 5% metal content and density of 3500 kg/m³. The reserve of the ore body is _____ million ton(s) (give answer in two decimal places).",
      "option" : [],
      "answer": "0.22"
    }
  ],
  "2018": [
    {
      "question": "Choose the characteristic mineral(s) formed in the supergene enriched zone of a sulphide deposit. (Multiple Select Question)",
      "options": [
        "Psilomelane",
        "Covellite",
        "Cassiterite",
        "Chalcocite"
      ],
      "answer": ["Covellite", "Chalcocite"]
    },
    {
      "question": "The valency of iron in hematite is _____.",
      "options": [],
      "answer": "3"
    },
    {
      "question": "600 tons of low grade iron ore (40% Fe) are blended with 400 tons of high grade iron ore (65% Fe). The grade of the blended ore is _____ % Fe (answer in one decimal place).",
      "options": [],
      "answer": "50"
    },
    {
      "question": "Petroleum is NOT commercially produced from:",
      "options": [
        "Krishna–Godavari basin",
        "Cauvery–Palar basin",
        "Cambay basin",
        "Vindhyan basin"
      ],
      "answer" : "Vindhyan basin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the mineral deposits in Group I with corresponding Indian occurrences in Group II. Group I: P. Iron Q. Uranium R. Manganese S. Baryte Group II: 1. Mangampet, Andhra Pradesh 2. Balaghat, Madhya Pradesh 3. Narwa Pahar, Jharkhand\n4. Hospet, Karnataka",
      "options": [
        "P-1, Q-3, R-4, S-2",
        "P-4, Q-1, R-3, S-2",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
        "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1"
      ],
      "answer" : "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following processes is responsible for the formation of syngenetic Ni-Cu sulphide ore in gabbro-noritic rocks?",
      "options": [
        "Hydrothermal replacement",
        "Volcanic exhalation",
        "Liquid immiscibility",
        "Contact metamorphism"
      ],
      "answer":"Liquid immiscibility"
    }
  ],
  "2019": [
    {
      "question": "An ore mineral has the following physical properties: (1) metallic lustre, (2) steel-grey color, (3) two sets of octahedral cleavage, (4) high specific gravity, and (5) makes mark on paper. Identify the ore mineral.",
      "options": [
        "Sphalerite",
        "Magnetite",
        "Galena",
        "Bornite"
      ],
      "answer": "Galena"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the fundamental constituent of humic coal?",
      "options": [
        "Mineral matter",
        "Macerals",
        "Lithotype",
        "Kerogen"
      ],
      "answer" : "Macerals"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the fuels in Group I with corresponding areas of occurrence in Group II. Group I: P. Uranium Q. Lignite R. Bituminous Coal S. Petroleum Group II: 1. Vastan, Gujarat 2. Singrauli, Madhya Pradesh 3. Digboi, Assam 4. Jaduguda, Jharkhand",
      "options": [
        "P-4, Q-1, R-3, S-2",
        "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
        "P-2, Q-4, R-1, S-3"
      ],
      "answer" : "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following are the characteristics of a typical porphyry copper deposit?",
      "options": [
        "I. Associated with granitic rocks",
        "II. Low-grade and high tonnage of ore",
        "III. Presence of alteration zones",
        "IV. Occurrence in convergent tectonic setting"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "III. Presence of alteration zones"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the metal deposits in Group I with the corresponding processes in Group II. Group I: P. Aluminum Q. Iron R. Tungsten S. Thorium Group II: 1. Mechanical concentration 2. Contact metasomatism 3. Residual concentration A4. Chemical sedimentation",
      "options": [
        "P-1, Q-3, R-2, S-4",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-1, S-2",
        "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-1"
      ],
      "answer" : "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1"
    },
    {
      "question": "A tabular ore body of 9 km² area and an average thickness of 9 m has a density of 3000 kg/m³. The tonnage (in million tonnes) of the ore body is ____.",
      "optios": [],
      "answer": "243"
    }
  ],
  "2020": [
    {
      "question": "The correct pair of metal and the ore mineral is:",
      "options": [
        "Nickel - Sphalerite",
        "Tin - Cassiterite",
        "Zinc - Pyrolusite",
        "Lead - Bornite"
      ],
      "answer": "Tin - Cassiterite"
    },
    {
      "question": "The wt.% (correct to two decimal places) of Cu in chalcopyrite (CuFeS₂) (atomic weight of Cu=63.55, Fe=55.85, S=32.07) is _____.",
      "options": [],
      "answer": "34.62"
    },
    {
      "question": "Randomly oriented ore-bearing veinlets in a mass of rock are known as:",
      "options": [
        "en echelon veins",
        "sheeted veins",
        "lode",
        "stockworks"
      ],
      "answer": "stockworks"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following oil field is NOT located in the western part of India?",
      "options": [
        "Bombay High",
        "Ankleshwar",
        "Gandhar",
        "Moran"
      ],
      "answer": "Moran"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the mineral/metal deposit in Group I with the corresponding Indian occurrence in Group II. Group I Diamond Iron Fluorite Copper Group II Malanjkhand Wajrakarur Dalli-Rajhara Ambadongar.",
      "options": [
        "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1",
        "P-3, Q-4, R-1, S-2",
        "P-2, Q-1, R-4, S-3",
        "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-1"
      ],
      "answer": "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Choose the correct statement(s): (Multiple Select Question)",
      "options": [
        "Stratiform chromite deposits form by weathering of ultramafic rocks.",
        "Skarn deposits mostly form in calcareous host rocks in contact with felsic intrusives.",
        "Nickeliferous laterite is a type of placer deposit.",
        "Gold-bearing vein deposits can form from hydrothermal solutions."
      ],
      "answer": ["Skarn deposits mostly form in calcareous host rocks in contact with felsic intrusives.", "Gold-bearing vein deposits can form from hydrothermal solutions."]
    },
    {
      "question": "A spherical ore body (diameter = 40m) has 7% metal content and density of 3300 kg/m³. The reserve (in tonne) of the ore body is ______.",
      "options": [],
      "answer": "110628.57"
    }
  ],
  "2021": [],
  "2022": [],
  "2023": [],
  "2024": [],
  "2025": []
}
